Guide to the Leonard Bloomfield Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leonard Bloomfield papers
1909-1950
MS 635
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
Correspondence, writings, and notebooks entirely related to his professional interest in languages and linguistics. The largest part of the papers consist of a sequence of forty-four notebooks, each devoted to a language or a linguistic problem. The phonology and morphology of twenty-one languages are covered in these volumes. Three unpublished articles by Bloomfield are also in the papers.
Bloomfield, Leonard, 1887-1949
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Leonard Bloomfield, 1949.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers of the linguist Leonard Bloomfield are entirely devoted to his professional interests. Aside from seven letters from other linguists, the papers consist of a few unpublished works by Bloomfield and two items by other linguists, and of forty-four notebooks compiled by Bloomfield. These have as their subject matter the phonology and morphology of a wide variety of languages. It seems likely that these notebooks were used by Bloomfield in preparing his publications. The two earliest volumes contain class notes.
Indians of North America -- Languages; Linguistics; Literature -- History and criticism; Reading; Educators; Linguists; Bloomfield, Leonard, 1887-1949; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Burke, John, 1945 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lo Ch'ang-p'ei, 1946 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Uhlenbeck, C. C., 1946 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vlekke, Bernard, 1943 April-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Yrizas, Pedro de, 1950 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings
    - Teaching Children to Read [typescript], 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 8)
    - The Benares Commentary [typescript], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Draft article on education [ms], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notebooks
    - "Gothic", 1909-1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Geschichte der deutschen Sprache", 1913 September-1914 June (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Burmese", 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Arabic, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Dutch, undated (Box 2, Folder 15 - 20)
    - Finnish, undated (Box 3, Folder 21 - 22)
    - German, undated (Box 3, Folder 23 - 24)
    - Gothic, undated (Box 3, Folder 25 - 27)
    - Gypsy, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Lithuanian, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Middle High German, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Modern Greek, undated (Box 3, Folder 31 - 32)
    - Ojibwa, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "Old Icelandic: Description of Inflection", undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Old Icelandic: Descriptive Grammar, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "Old Icelandic: History", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Pānini, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Polish, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Potawatomi, undated (Box 4, Folder 39 - 40)
    - Proto-Germanic and Old High Germanic, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Russian, undated (Box 4, Folder 42 - 47)
    - Scandinavian, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - "Scandinavian literature", undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Spanish, undated (Box 5, Folder 50 - 51)
    - Swedish, undated (Box 5, Folder 52 - 53)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Writings of others
    - Pike, Kenneth L.: "A Monolingual Approach to a Foreign Language" [typescript], 1943 October 16 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Anonymous: "Japanese Notes" [typescript], undated (Box 5, Folder 56 - 59)